So as a result of
rightly practicing virtue and also
restraint, a sense of peace and relaxation can
a sense of peace and relaxation can
start to arise.
But how does one distinguish that kind
of peace
from the peace that is the result of
gaining the right view?
So uh well
the piece of the of the right view it's
not just the peace that you have on
account of virtuous behavior
and wholesome lifestyle. It's also the
peace on account of not being moved by
the possibilities of things not going
your way. So of losing things of
experiencing impermanence and so on.
those possibilities do not um disturb
the mind. In other words, mind has been
trained in regard to them. And that's
the level of the right view. When the
suffering cannot arise not just because
everything is fine now, but because even
if things were not fine, you would be
unable to to to uh to crave
um to the degree um
that the that the kind of that putenous
dooka would have arisen.
So in other words like putujana craves
against his feelings because he hasn't
understood the nature of feelings.
So it's not just about like oh
diminishing and reducing the outputs of
your craving. It's about understanding
the nature of where that craving is.
So the more you understand the nature of
your feelings, the more you understand
the impermanence which can only be done
on the basis of not running away from
them, not covering up, not managing
um but being able to like withstand them
to the full extent. That's how you get
to see the craving that kind of resides
there so to speak. There was always in
regard to what's being felt
and when someone has been
practicing that virtue and that
restraint but they still have doubts.
>> Well, exactly. So, you have to practice
virtue and sense restraint but in and of
itself that will not guarantee you the
right view. So on top of your virtue and
sense restraint, you have to be
frequently recollecting
the impermanence
uh loss of their things and not running
away from it and not just trying to
psychologize it and sort of create an
emotional buffer to prepare yourself
when it comes so that I can bear it. And
it's like no no you want to be bringing
it up so that your mind gets used to it
so that it stops u gratuously by default
they stops resisting it all those
perceptions perceptions of uh change
perceptions of losing perceptions of
health percept losing the health and
life and so on like those are the
contemplations that whether a
householder or a big they you have to do
it if you want to get the right view
because the reason people don't have the
right view is because they don't allow
allow these perceptions to u to land
like everybody's experiencing them but
the point is they're experiencing them
with the attitude of I must get rid of
this as soon as it's felt I must manage
this as soon as it arises I must cover
this up um with with uh by any means
necessary any practice any technique
anything I can do to keep the lid on
this it's like no it's the opposite you
should be able to take it on in a
fullest extent the perception of
impermanence and not be moved by it.
Because the suffering does not come from
things changing. It doesn't come from
perceiving impermanence. It comes from
craving against what's felt when you
perceive impermanence.
So you're resisting the discomfort of
it. And therefore, you're avoiding those
perceptions. So that's the fundamental difference
So that's the fundamental difference
between somebody who who's like
perfectly virtuous and sensory trained
but without the right view and the one
with the right view. And that would also
be the difference even between somebody
who is perfectly virtuous and restrained
without the right view and somebody with
the right view who is sort of lapsing in
their virtue and so on. Um
like externally they might not be
maintaining the standard as wholesomely
as the former person the but internally
they have dug deeper.
So they're not just keeping it at the
arms length and then hoping that the the
virtue and and and um sense restraint
will just magically make the mind sort
of uh not be affected by these
perceptions. It will help. Sure. All of that helps to
It will help. Sure. All of that helps to
not be affected. But fundamentally in
order to uproot it, in order to
understand it, you really need to be
taking on those perceptions and as the
suta says frequently dwelling on them.
like basically conditioning your mind to
stop, you know, looking away and
twitching when those when those
perceptions come up.
And now when someone is making effort to
practice these contemplations, but the
whole thing just begins to feel sort of
numb or it or it doesn't touch you in
the same way as it did before. Is that
necessarily a sign of progress or could
there be still like somebody just took a
wrong turn with all of this somewhere?
>> Well, it wouldn't I don't know if I
would I don't know if I would say took a
wrong turn. If somebody's giving the
precepts and practicing these
reflections, yeah, things might become
dry and they might not feel it and so
on, which means basically it's not like
they took the wrong turn, but it's more
like uh they are not uh um they're not
making it personal enough.
So that's the difference because again
as long as you're not sapan or hired
there are going to be things obvious
things that you're covering up and using
as a as a safety sort of zone and a
safety net. And even when you then
practice and contemplate you leave those
things out. So if you want to make your
practice alive just to reinclude those
things and start questioning them things
that you you just deem uh have to be
certain way and then you just start
asking well do they do they have to be
that way?
Oh I can't practice because of such and
such. Well
that that is what you chose to be the
reason. But
can you really not practice?
Can you really not upgrade the precepts?
Can you really not endure those states
of mind? You can, but you fail. But
there's a difference between trying
genuinely and failing and then trying
failing and then convincing yourself
that it can't be done. That's the
difference. So even if you keep failing,
but for as long as you're trying to do
it, you're kind of aiming in the right
direction. But if you say from the
start, oh, it can't be done. Even if
you're not failing, you're not doing it
>> because again, you're not allowing it to
land deep enough where it should land.
>> Yeah. So then a person has to be quite
honest with themselves and deliberately
seek out those areas that you sort of
intuitively don't really want to go
>> 100%. That's like nobody else. I mean,
people can point it to you or something,
but fundamentally that's the type of
work that only a person can do for
themselves. Nobody can do it for you.
You know, you can learn about it. As I
said, others can point what to look for,
but unless you are doing it, nobody can
kind of uncover all of that for you.
Impossible.